RG 069:145, Charles F. Watrous Papers
Connecticut State Library
Charles F. Watrous papers
1917-1942
Connecticut State Library
Watrous, Charles F.
1 cubic foot
Corporal Charles F. Watrous was a World War I veteran who served in Company F of the 102 Infantry in the American Expeditionary Forces in France.
RG069_145
2009-002
Biographical Note
Corporal Charles F. Watrous was a World War I veteran who served in Company F of the 102 Infantry in the American Expeditionary Forces in France. Charles enlisted in the National Guard on July 16, 1917 in New Haven, Connecticut. He saw combat service in 1918, fought in the Chateau Thierry and Meuse-Argonne offensives, was wounded in the arm by gun fire on July 25, 1918, and received a Purple Heart. Corporal Charles F. Watrous was honorably discharged from the United States Army on April 29, 1919. He later served in the Milford Fire Department and Connecticut National Guard and was a guard officer during World War II.
Scope and Content
The papers consist of the enlistment record and honorable discharge paper for Corporal Charles F. Watrous, photographs, two small pocket diaries, Connecticut State Guard identity card, Social Security cards, buttons, and medals. The bulk of the photographs are from the World War I period, although two others date from 1941-42.
Index Terms
Subjects:
World War, 1914-1918 -- Connecticut; Château-Thierry, Battle of, Château-Thierry, France, 1918; Argonne, Battle of the, France, 1918; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 102nd. Company F; Connecticut. National Guard. Regiment, 2nd. Company F; Connecticut. National Guard; USS Lenape; Lenape (Steamship); Adriatic (Ship)
Places:
New York (N.Y.); Milford (Conn.); New Haven (Conn.); Essex (Conn.); Fort Totten (N.Y.); Halifax (N.S.); Liverpool (England); Southampton (England); Le Havre (France); Niantic (Conn.); Concord (Mass.)
Persons:
Watrous, Charles F.
Document Types:
Diaries; Military records; Photographs; Medals; Badges; Identity cards; Buttons (information artifacts); Tie clasps
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Alternative Form Available
Transcripts of the two diaries completed by volunteer Jeremy Schmitt are included in the papers.
Provenance
The papers were donated by Arthur Watrous, a nephew of Charles’s, to the Connecticut State Library in July 2008.
Container List
- Papers, 1917-1942
  - Honorable discharge papers, 1919 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles F. Watrous portraits, undated; 3 black-and-white photographs (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Diaries, Connecticut State Guard Identity Card, and Social Security cards, circa 1917-1936, undated; 2 diaries, 2 Social Security cards, and 1 identity card (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Charles F. Watrous portraits, undated; 8 black-and-white photographs (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Key, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Brass eagle buttons, undated; 5 buttons (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Brass eagle buttons (small), undated; 4 buttons (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bronze eagle button (large), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bronze eagle buttons, undated; 4 buttons (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bronze eagle buttons (small), undated; 7 buttons (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Milford Fire Department badge, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - US CT 242 brass pin, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Southern Missionary College 20 years pin, circa 1922 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Brass pin with retracting chain, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Brass bracelet and chain, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Connecticut State Guard pins, undated; 4 pins (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Brass pin, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Silver tie clip with turquoise, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - World War I Victory Medal and ribbon, undated; 1 medal with 4 Army battle clasps and 1 ribbon with 4 bronze service stars (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    The medal contains the following 4 Army battle clasps: Champagne-Marne; Aisne-Marne; Meuse-Argonne; and Defensive Sector.
  - World War State of Connecticut for Service medal, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Purple Heart, circa 1932 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    The Purple Heart is in a small purple box with the following side label, "The Bailey, Banks & Biddle Co. 2-12-32 Phila. Quartermaster Depot Purple Heart Medal No. 35H32". The back of the Purple Heart is engraved with the name of Charles F. Watrous.
  - American Legion 20th Anniversary Armistice Day medal coin, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Course Six - First Service Command Tacticle School Concord, Mass., 1942 August; 1 rolled black-and-white photograph (Box 2)
  - Connecticut State Guard - Camp Hurley - Niantic, Conn., 1941 August 4; 1 rolled black-and-white photograph (Box 2)